Guide to the Alan Hovhaness Letters to Judith Malina
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Alan Hovhaness letters to Judith Malina
1953-1959
YCAL MSS 359
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.42
(1 box)
The collection consists of Alan Hovhaness's letters to Judith Malina with accompanying notes, poems, photographs, and printed material. Two letters from Hovhaness to Malina's husband, Julian Beck, and a carbon copy of his response are also included.
Hovhaness, Alan, 1911-2000
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Margolis & Moss on the Adele Gutman Nathan Theatrical Collection Fund, 2009.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Alan Hovhaness (1911-2000)
Alan Hovhaness was a prolific American composer whose works were influenced by both Western and non-Western musical traditions. He composed over sixty symphonies including Symphony No. 2, Mysterious Mountain, which was premiered by Leopold Stokowski in his debut with the Houston Symphony in 1955. Hovhaness also wrote incidental music for Clifford Odets' Broadway play The Flowering Peach and composed music for several of Martha Graham's choreographic works. In 1952 he met Judith Malina, co-director of the Living Theatre, through his wife Serafina Ferrante Hovhaness, who performed with the company. Following their meeting Hovhaness performed benefit concerts and composed incidental music for the Living Theatre production of Strindberg's Ghost Sonata.
Judith Malina (1926-)
Judith Malina, actor, writer, and director, co-directed the Living Theatre, a New York-based avant-garde theatre company, with her husband Julian Beck from 1947 until Beck's death in 1985. Malina and company member Hanon Reznikov (who became her second husband) co-directed the company until his death in 2008, after which she assumed sole directorship.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of handwritten letters from Hovhaness to Judith Malina in which he expresses, in prose as well as poetry, his ardent love for her. The letters also include comments regarding his travels, compositions, and his desire to collaborate on various works with Malina. Each letter is enclosed in a sheet of paper annotated with date and city by Malina. Accompanying the letters are two drafts of letters from Malina to Hovhaness; two letters from Hovhaness to Julian Beck regarding a production with a carbon copy of Beck's response; photographs of Hovhaness, his wife Serafina, and Malina; lists of Hovhaness's performances, and printed notices, performance programs, and press clippings; and copies of typed transcripts of the Hovhaness letters annotated by Malina.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically.
Composers -- United States; Photographs; Beck, Julian, 1925-1985; Hovhaness, Alan, 1911-2000; Malina, Judith, 1926-2015; Living Theatre (New York, N.Y.)
- Hovhaness Letters and Accompanying Material, 1953-59; 0.42
  - Hovhaness letters to Judith Malina with cover sheets annotated by Malina, 1953-58, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
  - Poems and quotes sent by Hovhaness to Judith Malina, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Drafts of two letters from Malina to Hovhaness; three Haikus written by Malina in Hovhaness's hand; and carbon copy of Malina letter to a Mr. Adkins regarding a photograph of Serafina Hovhaness, 1959 Feb (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters to Julian Beck with carbon copy of Beck letter to Hovhaness, 1959 Feb (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Photographs of Hovhaness, his wife Serafina, and Judith Malina, 1955, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Lists of Hovhaness's performances in his hand; printed performance notices and programs, 1953-56 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Some additional momentos" consisting of envelopes addressed to Malina in Hovhaness's hand, 1954-58 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Press clippings regarding Hovhaness and Thornton Wilder, 1954-57 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Carbon copies of typed transcripts of Hovhaness letters with annotations in Malina's hand, 1953-58, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Photocopies of typed transcripts of Hovhaness letters with annotations in Malina's hand, 1953-58, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)